<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Medical Tutors</title>
	<atom:link href="/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>E-Learning for Medical Experts</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 09:37:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.4.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/cropped-Medicaltutors-03-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Medical Tutors</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>SKIN CANCER: Introduction and Overview</title>
		<link>/skin-cancer-introduction-and-overview/</link>
					<comments>/skin-cancer-introduction-and-overview/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10611</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Skin cancer is the abnormal growth of skin cells that develops on the human skin whenever it’s exposed to the sun (ultraviolet). It can also emanate from other skin – part of the body that isn’t necessarily exposed to the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-11504" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer.jpg 1000w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer-768x513.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer-440x294.jpg 440w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer-374x250.jpg 374w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/07/skincancer-600x401.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Skin cancer is the abnormal growth of skin cells that develops on the human skin whenever it’s exposed to the sun (ultraviolet). It can also emanate from other skin – part of the body that isn’t necessarily exposed to the sun. Unlike other types of cancer affecting humans, most cases of skin cancers&#8230;</p>
</div></div>



<p>Skin cancer is the abnormal growth of skin cells that develops on the human skin whenever it’s exposed to the sun (ultraviolet). It can also emanate from other skin – part of the body that isn’t necessarily exposed to the sun. Unlike other types of cancer affecting humans, most cases of skin cancers are locally destructive cancerous i.e. malignant growth of the skin, originating from the superficial layer of the skin called the epidermis.</p>



<p>According to the World Health Organisation (W.H.O), there are basically two types of skin cancer; Non – melanoma skin cancer which comprises of Basal Cell Carcinomas and Squamous Cell Carcinomas; and also the Melanoma skin cancer. The Basal cell carcinoma is the most common form of skin cancer, followed by Squamous cell carcinoma (second most common) – originating from the skin cells. The third most common is the Melanoma skin cancer, which originates from the pigment – producing skin cells; although less common among humans but more dangerous than the other two.</p>



<p>In the year 2018, Melanoma of the skin is the 19th most commonly occurring cancer in men and&nbsp;women, involving over 300,000 new cases .Non-melanoma skin cancer is the 5th most commonly occurring cancer in men and women, with over 1 million diagnoses worldwide in 2018, although this is likely to be an underestimate. Currently, between 2 and 3 million non-melanoma skin cancers and 132,000 melanoma skin cancers occur globally each year.</p>



<p>Skin cancer affects people of all skin tones, including those with darker complexions. When melanoma occurs in people with dark skin tones, it&#8217;s more likely to occur in areas not normally exposed to the sun, such as the palms of the hands and soles of the feet.</p>



<p><strong>Is Skin Cancer Hereditary?</strong></p>



<p>According to the World Health Organisation and Skin Cancer Foundation, it has been made known that skin cancers can’t be considered to be inherited since it is majorly caused by exposure to ultraviolet light exposure. Although not supporting the fact that genetics should be considered in skin cancer cases due to the fact that skin cancer is much common among poorly pigmented individuals, yet there are some very rare cases of genetic syndromes that have resulted in an increased number of skin cancers in people affected. This is usually caused by DNA mutations induced by ultraviolet light affecting cells of the epidermis.</p>



<p><strong>Types of Skin Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Early explained, there are two basic types of skin cancers; Non – melanoma skin cancer and Melanoma skin cancer.</p>



<p><strong>Non – Melanoma Skin Cancers</strong></p>



<p>The non – melanoma skin cancers comprise of Basal Cell Carcinomas; and the Squamous Cell Carcinomas. These two form of non – melanoma skin cancers are rarely harmful or dangerous but its treatment might cause skin disfiguring. Non – melanoma skin cancers are the most frequent on parts of the body that are commonly exposed to the suns i.e. ears, eyes, neck etc; with the ultraviolet light causing lasting damage.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Basal Cell Carcinomas:</strong>&nbsp;This is a type of skin cancer that begins from the basal cells – a skin cell that produces new skin cells as the old ones die off. It is the most common form of skin cancer and the most frequently occurring form of all cancers. It often appears as a slight transparent bump on the skin.</li></ul>



<p>Basal Cell Carcinomas occurrence is due to constant exposure to the ultraviolet light of the sun and could cause; and avoiding the sun (through the use of sunglasses; wearing of caps or long clothing) can help prevent it occurrence on an individual skin. Due to its nature of slow growth, basal cell carcinoma is usually curable and cause minimal damage to the skin once they are diagnosed and treated early.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Squamous Cell Carcinomas:</strong>&nbsp;This is the second most common form of skin cancers. It develops in the squamous cells that make up the middle and outer layers of the human skin, characterized by the abnormal growth in the squamous cells. Although not life threatening, yet it can be quite aggressive if untreated, thus spreading to other layers of the skin causing serious complications.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Melanoma Skin Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Melanoma skin cancer is the most serious and dangerous form of skin cancer; although far less prevalent than Non – melanoma skin cancer due to its ability to spread to other organs more rapidly if not treated at its early stage; it is the cause of major death from skin cancer. It develops from the melanocytes cell which is responsible for producing melanin.</p>



<p>The melanin is pigment that gives the skin its natural colour. There are two types of melanin: eumelanin and pheomelanin. When skin is exposed to ultraviolet radiation / light from the sun or tanning beds, it causes skin damage that triggers the melanocytes to produce more melanin, but only the eumelanin pigment attempts to protect the skin by causing the skin to darken or tan. Melanoma occurs when DNA damage from burning or tanning due to UV radiation triggers changes (mutations) in the melanocytes, resulting in uncontrolled cellular growth.</p>



<p>The risk of melanoma seems to be increasing in people under 40, especially women. Knowing the warning signs of skin cancer can help ensure that cancerous changes are detected and treated before the cancer has spread. Melanoma can be treated successfully if it is detected early.</p>



<p><strong>Other Less Form of Skin Cancers</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Kaposi Sarcoma:</strong>&nbsp;This is a rare form of skin cancer that develops in the skin’s blood vessels, causing red or purple patches on the skin or mucous membranes. It occurs in people with weakened immune systems like AIDS.</li><li><strong>Merkel Cell Carcinoma:</strong>&nbsp;This is a rare type of skin&nbsp;cancer&nbsp;that usually appears as a flesh-colored or bluish-red nodule, often on your face, head or neck. It is quite aggressive with a high risk of recurring and spreading across the skin.</li><li><strong>Sebaceous Gland Carcinoma:&nbsp;</strong>This is an uncommon and aggressive skin cancer that begins in the oil glands of the skin. It is known to usually affect the eyelids.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Skin Cancer in Nigeria</strong></p>



<p>Skin cancer is the most common malignancies in the world today with over three million non – melanoma skin cancers and 132,000 melanoma cases diagnosed every year.</p>



<p>Unlike other part of the world, skin cancer is less common in Nigeria, but it does occur among its citizens especially the albinos in the country. It is estimated that there are over 65,000 cases of skin cancer in Nigeria annually giving a projected annual incidence of 52 in 100,000.</p>



<p>Skin cancer is a major cause of morbidity and mortality in Albinos who develop premalignant and malignant lesions at a younger age and suffer from advanced skin cancers in the third to fourth decade of life. Unlike most form of skin cancer, Albinism is genetically inherited, and there are some quite numbers of them in the world. For Albinism in Nigeria, there is an estimated incidence of 1 to 15,000, especially in the Southern part of the country.</p>



<p>As stated earlier, lack of melanin and exposure to intense ultraviolet radiation increase the risk of developing skin cancer; therefore the lack of melanin in Albinos increases the risk of developing skin cancer by 1,000 fold as compared with the general Nigerian population.</p>



<p>Skin Cancer Worldwide Statistics:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wcrf.org/dietandcancer/cancer-trends/skin-cancer-statistics">https://www.wcrf.org/dietandcancer/cancer-trends/skin-cancer-statistics</a></p>



<p><em><strong>[Next Article on Skin Cancer &#8211; Causes and Risk Factors of Skin Cancer]</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/skin-cancer-introduction-and-overview/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lung Cancer &#8211; Diagnosis and Treatment</title>
		<link>/lung-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/</link>
					<comments>/lung-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10614</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For the best and optimum recovery from lung cancer, it is recommended that individuals get themselves screened whenever there are symptoms of lung cancer. Diagnosis Lung cancer is a condition that allows the cells in the lungs to divide uncontrollably, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-11536" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer.jpg 1000w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer-768x513.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer-440x294.jpg 440w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer-374x250.jpg 374w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/lung-cancer-600x401.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">For the best and optimum recovery from lung cancer, it is recommended that individuals get themselves screened whenever there are symptoms of lung cancer.</p>
</div></div>



<p><strong>Diagnosis</strong></p>



<p>Lung cancer is a condition that allows the cells in the lungs to divide uncontrollably, causing growth of tumors around the lungs, and thus reducing an individual inability to breathe. This is why it is important for current and past smokers (and second – hand smokers too) to get their lung screened for possible lung cancer.</p>



<p>Individuals who have a high risk of having lung cancer or probably via family history; it is of importance to consider an annual or monthly screening. Although lung cancer screening is usually offered to older persons ranging from 55 years and above, who had smoked for many years or recently quit.</p>



<p>Most medical practitioners tend to apply the physical examination first before any other screening exercise, so as to detect any abnormal growth or swollen lymph above the collarbone, around the abdomen because some screening exercise might fail to see any form of growth if the tumor hasn’t gotten bigger. Also, weak breathing, abnormal sounds in the lungs, weakness or swollen veins in the arms or certain changes in the fingernails might create a suspicion for lung tumor.</p>



<p>The moment a suspicion is created, the medical doctor / practitioner might suggest some series of test so as to determine the presence of cancerous cells. And these tests / screening methods may include:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Imaging Tests</strong></li></ul>



<p>Imaging test such as X-ray image helps to show the image of the lungs, and reveals any abnormal growth in the system. Computed tomography (CT) and positron emission tomography (PET) scans would also help to reveal areas of lung tissues with cancer in the body. Some medical practitioners use these scans to determine the progress in cancer treatment.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Sputum Cytology (Lab Testing)</strong></li></ul>



<p>Once a patient starts having coughed which produces sputum, the doctor might recommend a sputum or blood testing so as to reveal the presence of lung cancer cells. This will help the doctor carefully analyze the cancer cells, revealing what type of lung cancer present and it what stage. It also help to address the cells and determine the prognosis and treatment required.</p>



<p>Once lung cancer has been diagnosed, medical doctor will work to determine the extent (stage) of the cancer. Staging the type of cancer present helps to determine the best and appropriate treatment available.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Biopsy (Tissue Sampling)</strong></li></ul>



<p>Once a suspicion is created, a doctor might recommend having a sample of abnormal cells in the body to be removed; and this process is called biopsy.</p>



<p>Biopsy can be conducted in a number of ways, including bronchoscopy where the abnormal areas are examined using a lighted tube passed into the lungs from the throat. Also mediastinoscopy, in which an incision is made at the base of the neck and surgical tools are inserted behind the breastbone to take tissue samples from lymph nodes is also an option. Another option is needle biopsy, in which your doctor uses X-ray or&nbsp;CT&nbsp;images to guide a needle through the chest wall and into the lung tissue to collect suspicious cells.</p>



<p>A biopsy sample may also be taken from lymph nodes or other areas where cancer has spread, such as the liver.</p>



<p><strong>Stages of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Staging lung cancer can help determine how far or severe the cancer has spread in the body system, thus help guide in the treatment plans. The chance of cancer treatment being successful is dependent on when the lung cancer was diagnosed and treated in its early stages, before spreading to other parts. Due to the fact that lung cancer doesn’t cause obvious symptoms in the human body in its early stages, diagnosis often comes after it might have spread.</p>



<p>There are two types of lung cancer: non – small cell lung cancer and small lung cancer; and each one of these lung cancers are staged differently.</p>



<p><strong>Types of Lung Cancer Stages</strong></p>



<p><strong>Non – Small Cell Lung Cancer Stage</strong></p>



<p>Non – small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is the most common type of lung cancer among individuals than the small cell lung cancer (SCLC), and staging it, medical doctors might need to use imaging scans to determine its clinical stage. This might involve the use of biopsy, which would help determine the stage of the cancer.</p>



<p>Usually, the most common staging method for NSCLC is the TNM staging method with numbers X, 0, 1, 2 etc. so as to differentiate the presence of tumors in the lung or its size. Also the general staging method might also be used.</p>



<p><strong>Staging</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Occult Stage:</strong>&nbsp;At this stage, the cancer cells can be picked up in the mucus an individual coughs up. The tumor presence can’t be seen on any form of imaging scans or biopsy. This is also called the hidden cancer.</li><li><strong>Stage 0:</strong>&nbsp;At this stage a tumor can be found but it’s relatively small; and the cancer cells in the lung haven’t spread into the deeper part of the lung nor has it spread outside the lungs.</li><li><strong>Stage I:</strong>&nbsp;Cancer has been found in the lung tissues but not yet in the lymph nodes.</li><li><strong>Stage II:</strong>&nbsp;Cancer is in the lung and lymph nodes in the middle of the chest</li><li><strong>Stage IIIA:</strong>&nbsp;Cancer is found in lymph nodes, but only on the same side of the chest where the cancer had first developed.</li><li><strong>Stage IIIB:</strong>&nbsp;The cancer has spread to other lymph nodes on the opposite side of the chest and other lymph nodes above the collarbone.</li><li><strong>Stage IV:</strong>&nbsp;The cancer has spread out to both lungs, and into other area around the lungs or distant organs.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Small Cell Lung Cancer Stages</strong></p>



<p>The moment an individual has been diagnosed with the Small Cell Lung Cancer (SCLC), the medical doctor may decide to use the TNM system of staging, after which he/she would divide the cancer into one of these two main stages.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Limited Stage:</strong>&nbsp;In this stage, the cancer can only be found in one lung and nearby lymph nodes which are on the same side of the chest, but it hasn’t spread to both lungs or past the lungs.</li><li><strong>Extensive Stage:</strong>&nbsp;Here, the tumor has spread throughout both lungs; to the lymph nodes of both lungs and the chest. It might have spread to the fluid around the lungs (called the pleura) and / or other organs of the body.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Treatment of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>The treatment for lung cancer is dependent on its present location and stage, and more importantly, the health condition of the individual involved. In most cases of lung cancer, surgery and radiation are the most commonly used treatment method, but there are many other treatments that are available for use.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Surgery</strong></li></ul>



<p>This involves the removal of cancerous lung tissue and tissues surrounding areas where the cancer might have spread. Procedures in surgery involve:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Wedge Resection:</strong>&nbsp;This surgery method involves the removal of a small section of the lung that contains the tumor and also some healthy tissues.</li><li><strong>Segmental Resection:</strong>&nbsp;This involves removing a larger portion of the lung, but not the entire lobe.</li><li><strong>Lobectomy:</strong>&nbsp;This is the removal of the entire lobe of one lung</li><li><strong>Pneumonectomy:</strong>&nbsp;In this form of surgery, the surgeon removes the entire lung. Individuals can live without a lung, that is if he/she has been living in a good health condition before the surgery; thus helping to improve the outcomes after lung removal.</li><li><strong>Radiation Therapy</strong></li></ul>



<p>This is using high energy rays to kill cancerous cells in the body. For individuals who with locally advanced lung cancer, radiation may be used before surgery or after surgery. It is often combined with chemotherapy treatments; but in situations where surgery isn’t an option to be used due to health conditions, radiation therapy combined with chemotherapy is usually advised.</p>



<p>Radiation therapy is also used on cancers that occur in one particular location and haven’t spread; and also used to help relieve certain symptoms like pain for advanced lung cancers.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy</strong></li></ul>



<p>Stereotactic body radiotherapy, also known as radiosurgery, is an intense radiation treatment that aims many beams of radiation from many angles at the cancer. Stereotactic body radiotherapy treatment is typically completed in one or a few treatments. It may be an option for people with small lung cancers who can&#8217;t undergo surgery. It may also be used to treat lung cancer that spreads to other parts of the body, including the brain.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Chemotherapy</strong></li></ul>



<p>Chemotherapy is the use drugs to eradicate / kill or shrink cancer cells in the body. It is often used after surgery to kill any cancer that may remain or before surgery to shrink cancers and make them easier to remove. It is usually used alone or combined with radiation therapy.</p>



<p>It has more significant impact on cancers that may have spread to other organs or parts of the body, requiring a mass body wide attack. Although Chemotherapy has its positive intervention but various side effects which include nausea and weight loss are usually present after its application.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Targeted Drug Therapy</strong></li></ul>



<p>Targeted drug treatments focus on specific abnormalities present within cancer cells. This is the use of particular medications that specifically target a particular behavior in cancer cells. By blocking these abnormalities, targeted drug treatments can cause cancer cells to die.</p>



<p>Many targeted therapy drugs are used to treat lung cancer, though most are reserved for people with advanced or recurrent cancer. Some of these targeted therapies only work in people whose cancer cells have certain genetic mutations.</p>



<p><strong>Prognosis</strong></p>



<p>Surviving Lung cancer can only be a successful for patients with lung cancer if it is being diagnosed at a very early stage. This will help increase the survival chance of such patients; and that’s why it’s important to seek medical advice once notable changes exist in the body.</p>



<p>According to recent studies by the American Lung Association, it was discovered that, the five – year survival rate for lung cancer is only achievable on 56% percent of cases that are detected locally i.e. within the lungs (Stages I – III). However, only 16% of lung cancer cases are diagnosed at this early stage. But in cases of tumors emerging from lung cancer that had moved to other parts of the body (Stage IV), the rate of survival is only 5%.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/lung-cancer-diagnosis-and-treatment/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clinical Features of Lung Cancer</title>
		<link>/clinical-features-of-lung-cancer/</link>
					<comments>/clinical-features-of-lung-cancer/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10617</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Have you ever wonder how lung cancer signs and symptoms presents itself in the human body? Most clinical cases of lung cancer presentation usually happens if the early signs and symptoms haven&#8217;t been properly taken care of when it ought [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-1204x804.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-11556" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-1204x804.jpg 1204w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-300x200.jpg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-768x513.jpg 768w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-1536x1026.jpg 1536w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-2048x1368.jpg 2048w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-700x466.jpg 700w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-440x294.jpg 440w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-374x250.jpg 374w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/08/clinical-lung-01-1-600x401.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1204px) 100vw, 1204px" /></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Have you ever wonder how lung cancer signs and symptoms presents itself in the human body? Most clinical cases of lung cancer presentation usually happens if the early signs and symptoms haven&#8217;t been properly taken care of when it ought to.</p>
</div></div>



<p><br>Lung cancer is the world third most diagnosed cancer among both genders (male or female). It is a cancer that starts from the lungs and often occurs among people who smokes. Nevertheless, there is a certain percentage of this type of cancer found in people who don’t smoke at all. Without proper treatment or preventive measures taken, it can become chronic; thereby leading to the cause of death among the individual.</p>



<p>Although, it doesn’t show early symptoms unlike breast cancer or prostate cancer among women and men respectively, yet it can be avoided if certain preventive measures are kept in place.</p>



<p><strong>Clinical Features of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Due to its relativeness of being asymptomatic (i.e. showing no symptoms except it gets to a critical stage) in individuals, lung cancer has some certain clinical features that showcases during certain stages as its danger loom.</p>



<p><strong>Symptoms of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Most lung cancers don’t cause any form of symptoms until they might have spread; yet some individual do have early lung cancer symptoms, making it easy to be diagnosed at an earlier stage when treatment is more likely to be effective.</p>



<p>Early Symptoms of Lung Cancer may include:</p>



<ul><li>A cough that keeps lingering or gets worse</li><li>Coughing up blood or phlegm (rust coloured sputum)</li><li>Shortness of breath</li><li>Hoarseness</li><li>Loss of appetite</li><li>Chest pain that worsens as one takes a deep breath, cough or laughs</li><li>Unexplained weight loss</li><li>Feeling weak or tired (fatigue)</li><li>Wheeziness</li><li>Recurrent respiratory infections such as bronchitis and pneumonia that keeps going back and forth</li></ul>



<p>Strongly suspect lung cancer if the above symptoms occur in a middle aged elderly person who smokes. Additional symptoms begin to emanate from the body the moment the cancer spreads and form new symptoms. These symptoms depend on the various part of organ it might have spread to. For example, if in the:</p>



<ul><li>Lymph Nodes: There are lumps building up, particularly around the collarbone and neck.</li><li>Bones: Consistent bone pain especially in the back, ribs or hips.</li><li>Liver: There is a yellowing or the skin and eyes (jaundice).</li><li>Brain or Spine: Constant headache, dizziness, numbness in the arms or legs and body balance issues.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Complications of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Lung cancer can cause complications in the human body, and they include:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Hemoptysis:</strong>&nbsp;Lung cancer can cause bleeding in the airway, which causes hemoptysis (coughing up blood). This bleeding can become severe and sometimes need treatments to control such bleeding.</li><li><strong>Shortness of Breath:</strong>&nbsp;Just like its symptoms, lung cancer complications can cause shortness of breath. Experiencing shortness of breath can be found in people with lung cancer once the cancer grows and block major airways. It can cause fluid to accumulate around the lungs, making it very hard for the affected lung to expand fully once an individual breathes.</li><li><strong>Pleural Effusion:</strong>&nbsp;Lung cancer can cause certain fluid to accumulate in most spaces that surrounds the affected lung in the pleural space. Causing shortness of breath, treatments are available to drain the fluid and reduce the reoccurrence of pleural effusion.</li><li><strong>Pain:</strong>&nbsp;Once lung cancer gets to the advanced stage or spread to other parts of the body such as the bone, it can cause pain and create a bad experience to the individual.</li><li><strong>Metastasis Lung Cancer:</strong>&nbsp;Lung cancer often spreads to other organs of the body, such as the brain and bones. And this causes pain, nausea, headaches or other signs and symptoms depending on what organ is affected. The moment it spreads beyond the lungs, it becomes non – curable.</li></ul>



<p><strong><em>[Next on Lung Cancer: Diagnosis and Treatment]</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/clinical-features-of-lung-cancer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>HEPATITIS E</title>
		<link>/hepatitis-e/</link>
					<comments>/hepatitis-e/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 14:22:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10620</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hepatitis E or HEV is an infectious diseases that can be contracted through contaminated water caused by faeces from an infected person to an uninfected person. It has similar features to the Hepatitis A virus (HAV) HEPATITIS E Hepatitis E [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Hepatitis-E.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10621"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Hepatitis E or HEV is an infectious diseases that can be contracted through contaminated water caused by faeces from an infected person to an uninfected person. It has similar features to the Hepatitis A virus (HAV)</p>
</div></div>



<p><strong>HEPATITIS E</strong></p>



<p>Hepatitis E is a liver disease that is caused by the hepatitis E virus (HEV), thus potentially causing swells and damages to the liver. In some people, this can lead to serious complications.</p>



<p>Just like the hepatitis A virus, the hepatitis E is spread by the fecally contaminated water i.e. stools of infected persons, within endemic areas or consumption of uncooked or undercooked meat (especially the contaminated ones); causing outbreaks in most developing countries. Hepatitis A is a self – limiting i.e. most individuals with hepatitis E gets better within weeks or months, though it doesn’t lead to long term illness or liver damage like other type of hepatitis yet it can be highly dangerous for pregnant women or individuals with weak immune systems (including elderly persons).</p>



<p>The virus has 4 different types: genotypes 1, 2, 3 and 4. Genotypes 1 and 2 have been found only in humans while genotypes 3 and 4 circulate in several animals (including pigs, wild boars, and deer) and thus causing diseases and occasionally infecting humans.</p>



<p>According to World Health Organisation, there is an estimated case of 20 million HEV infections worldwide, leading to an estimated 3.3 million symptomatic cases of hepatitis E. In 2015, hepatitis E caused approximately 44, 000 deaths (accounting for 3.3% of the mortality due to viral hepatitis).</p>



<p><strong>Transmission of Hepatitis E</strong></p>



<p>The hepatitis E virus is mainly transmitted through the faeces of an infected person to fecal contamination of drinking water. This is common in areas where poor environmental sanitation is practiced, also lacks good drinkable water. Other cases of transmission have been recorded but they are quite rare and accounts for limited number of clinical cases found among people. And they include:</p>



<ul><li>Digestion of uncooked meat or meat gotten from infected animals (i.e. pork or meat product gotten from deer)</li><li>Transmission from an infected pregnant woman to her unborn child</li><li>Blood transfusion from an infected person to an uninfected person</li></ul>



<p><strong>Geographical Distribution of Hepatitis E</strong></p>



<p>According to data gotten from W.H.O, hepatitis E infection is found globally in which two different patterns are observed and found in:</p>



<ul><li>Resources – poor areas with frequent contamination of water</li><li>Areas with safe drinking water</li></ul>



<p>The disease is common in low- and middle-income countries with limited access to essential water, sanitation, hygiene and health services. In these areas, the disease occurs both as outbreaks and as sporadic cases. The outbreaks usually follow periods of fecal contamination of drinking water supplies and may affect several hundred to several thousand persons. Some of these outbreaks have occurred in areas of conflict and humanitarian emergencies, such as war zones, and in camps for refugees or internally displaced populations, situations where sanitation and safe water supply pose special challenges.</p>



<p>Sporadic cases are also believed to be related to contamination of water, albeit at a smaller scale. The cases in these areas are caused mostly by infection with genotype 1 virus, and much less frequently by genotype 2 virus.</p>



<p>In areas with better sanitation and water supply, hepatitis E disease is infrequent, with only occasional sporadic cases. Most of these cases are caused by genotype 3 virus, and are triggered by infection with virus originating in animals, usually through ingestion of undercooked animal meat (including animal liver, particularly pork), and are not related to contamination of water or other foods.</p>



<p>Serological evidence of prior infection with the virus has been found in most areas, with higher seroprevalence rates (proportion of people who test positive for antibodies to HEV) in Asia and Africa. However, presence of these antibodies does not imply presence of or increased risk of disease. The usefulness of such data for epidemiological purposes may also be limited due to variable and possible sub-optimal performance of available serological assays, and possible disappearance of the antibody with the passage of time among those exposed to the virus.</p>



<p><strong>Symptoms of Hepatitis E</strong></p>



<p>The incubation period following exposure to HEV ranges from 2 to 10 weeks, with an average of 5 to 6 weeks. The infected persons excrete the virus beginning from a few days before to 3-4 weeks after onset of the disease.</p>



<p>In areas with high disease endemicity, symptomatic infection is most common in young adults aged 15–40 years. In these areas, although infection does occur in children, they often have either no symptoms or only a mild illness without jaundice which goes undiagnosed.</p>



<p>Typical signs and symptoms of hepatitis include:</p>



<ul><li>Mild&nbsp;fever</li><li>Feeling very&nbsp;tired</li><li>Less&nbsp;hunger</li><li>Feeling sick to your&nbsp;stomach</li><li>Throwing up</li><li>Belly&nbsp;pain</li><li>Dark pee</li><li>Light-colored poop</li><li>Skin rash&nbsp;or&nbsp;itching</li><li>Joint pain</li><li>Jaundice (yellowish&nbsp;skin&nbsp;or&nbsp;eyes)</li></ul>



<p><strong>Treatment of Hepatitis E</strong></p>



<p>At the moment there are no specific treatments required for hepatitis E, and because the disease is self – limiting, there isn’t any need for hospitalization or unnecessary medications. Apart from keep good personal hygiene, the following can also be adopted:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Eating Balanced Diet:</strong>&nbsp;Just like in a normal situation, individuals digesting a well varied balanced diet tend to have a good immune system, thus making the body an antigen to virus or any diseases; eating a balanced diet can help to treatment the hepatitis E virus from causing any form of damage to the body.</li><li><strong>Resting:</strong>&nbsp;Individuals infected with the hepatitis E virus need to properly rest because due to fatigue or body pain that hepatitis E might cause the body.</li><li><strong>Avoid Alcohol Intake:</strong>&nbsp;In case of hepatitis E, individuals must avoid all sort of alcohol since excessive alcohol can cause liver damage.</li><li><strong>Drinking of Plenty Liquids:</strong>&nbsp;In some individuals who tend to dehydrate easily whenever they are exhausted or tired, it is important and recommended that those who are infected with the hepatitis E virus need to drink plenty of liquids especially water so as to keep them hydrated.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Prevention of Hepatitis E</strong></p>



<p>According to W.H.O, prevention is the most effective approach against the disease. At the population level, transmission of HEV and hepatitis E disease can be reduced by:</p>



<ul><li>Maintaining quality standards for public water supplies</li><li>Establishing proper disposal systems for human faeces</li></ul>



<p>On an individual level, infection risk can be reduced by:</p>



<ul><li>Maintaining hygienic practices</li><li>Avoiding consumption of water and ice of unknown purity</li></ul>



<p>In 2011, a recombinant subunit vaccine to prevent hepatitis E virus infection was registered in China. It has not yet been approved in other countries.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/hepatitis-e/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>EPIDEMIOLOGY AND PREVENTION OF LUNG CANCER</title>
		<link>/epidemiology-and-prevention-of-lung-cancer/</link>
					<comments>/epidemiology-and-prevention-of-lung-cancer/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 12:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10623</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Due to the varying patterns in smoking of tobacco, which is primarily the cause of lung cancer among both sexes; it shouldn&#8217;t be ignored that lung cancer can also be diagnosed in individual who don&#8217;t smoke. Epidemiology In the world [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Epidemology.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10624"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Due to the varying patterns in smoking of tobacco, which is primarily the cause of lung cancer among both sexes; it shouldn&#8217;t be ignored that lung cancer can also be diagnosed in individual who don&#8217;t smoke.</p>
</div></div>



<p><strong>Epidemiology</strong></p>



<p>In the world today, lung cancer is the most common cancer and the leading cause of cancer death in men. It is also the third most common cancer (after breasts and colorectal cancers) and the second leading cause of cancer death (after breast cancer) in women. In 2008, lung cancer accounted for 13% or 1.6 million of total cancer cases and 18% or 1.4 million cancer-related deaths worldwide and also another 1.8 million cases in 2012, which accounted for 12.9% of the world’s total cancer incidence. The worldwide lung cancer mortality rate amounted to 1.59 million deaths in 2012, accounting for 19.4% of the total cancer deaths; thus making it the highest recorded cases and mortality rate from lung cancer. In 2018, the total cases of lung cancer had increased to 2.09 million in the world making it the number cancer cases, according to statistics by the World Health Organisation (WHO).</p>



<p>Over the last several decades, the incidence of adenocarcinoma of the lung has increased more rapidly than that of squamous cell carcinoma in men and especially in women. Adenocarcinoma has become the most common histologic cancer type diagnosed around the world since 2004, according to statistics from the World Health Organization. Sex differences in lung cancer mortality patterns also reflect historical differences between men and women in the increase and reduction of cigarette smoking over the last 50 years. In developing countries, not only the incidence but also the mortality rate of lung cancer has been increasing rapidly; incidence was ranked first in men and second in women.</p>



<p>Lung cancer incidence may also be related to air pollution caused by rapid and immature industrialization and continual increased use of automobiles in cities.</p>



<p>The global geographic distribution of lung cancer shows marked regional variation. In men, the highest incidence rates are observed in Central and Eastern Europe (53.5 per 100,000) and Eastern Asia (50.4 per 100,000). Notably low incidence rates are observed in Middle and Western Africa (2.0 and 1.7 per 100,000, respectively).</p>



<p><strong>Causes and Risk Factors of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Smoking is a known major risk factor for lung cancer but yet there are many etiological factors that can be seen as risk factors, and can be classed as changeable and non &#8211; changeable.</p>



<p><strong>Risk Factors That One Can Change</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Tobacco Smoke:</strong>&nbsp;Tobacco smoking or smoking is the leading risk factor that has been associated with the lung cancer, causing about 80% of lung cancer deaths in the world today. Only in rare occasion do individuals who have never smoked get diagnosed with lung cancer. The risk associated with a smoker is far higher than for non-smokers. The risk of lung cancer increases with the number of cigarettes smoked each day and the number of years having smoked. Quitting at any age can significantly thee risk of developing lung cancer.&nbsp;</li><li><strong>Secondhand Smoke:</strong>&nbsp;Some individuals who are non-smokers have been quite diagnosed with lung cancer. This is due to breathing in the smoke of others (called&nbsp;secondhand smoke&nbsp;or environmental tobacco smoke), which can increase the risk of developing lung cancer. Secondhand smoke is thought to cause more than 7,000 deaths from lung cancer each year. This should emphasis the need to ban smoking in public places.</li><li><strong>Exposure to Radon (Ionizing Radiation):</strong>&nbsp;Radon is produced by the natural breakdown of uranium in soil; rock and water that eventually becomes part of the air one breathe. Unsafe levels of radon can accumulate in any building, including homes; breathing it in exposes your lungs to small amounts of radiation, increasing a person’s risk of lung cancer. According to the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), radon is the second leading cause of lung cancer in the United States of America, and is the leading cause among non-smokers.</li><li><strong>Exposure to Asbestos:</strong>&nbsp;People who work with asbestos (such as in mines, a mill, textile plants, places where insulation is used and shipyards) are several times more likely to die of lung cancer. Lung cancer risk is much greater in workers exposed to asbestos who also smoke. It’s not clear how much low-level or short-term exposure to asbestos might raise lung cancer risk. People exposed to large amounts of asbestos also have a greater risk of developing mesothelioma, a type of cancer that starts in the pleura (the lining surrounding the lungs).</li><li><strong>Other Carcinogens:</strong>&nbsp;Also, carcinogens such as uranium, arsenic, beryllium, chromium compounds, and diesel exhaust, found in some workplaces, can also increase the chance of non-smokers to be diagnosed with lung cancer.</li><li><strong>Air Pollution:</strong>&nbsp;In cities, air pollution (especially near heavily trafficked roads) appears to raise the risk of lung cancer slightly. This risk is far less than the risk caused by smoking, but some researchers estimate that worldwide about 5% of all deaths from lung cancer may be due to outdoor air pollution. Reduction of air pollution using clean energy such as electric car, solar energy etc. can reduce the risk of lung cancer.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Risk Factors That Can’t Be Changed</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Previous Radiation Therapy to the Lungs:</strong>&nbsp;People who have had&nbsp;radiation therapy to the chest for other cancers&nbsp;are at higher risk for lung cancer, particularly if they smoke. Examples include people who have been treated for&nbsp;Hodgkin disease&nbsp;or women who get chest radiation after a mastectomy for&nbsp;breast cancer.</li><li><strong>Personal or Family History of Lung Cancer:</strong>&nbsp;For individuals who have had personal history of lung cancer, there is a high risk associated with developing lung cancer again. Individuals with brothers, sisters and parents who have had lung cancer have a slightly higher risk of lung cancer, especially if their relatives were diagnosed at a younger age. Researchers have found that genetics seems to play a role in some families with a strong history of lung cancer.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Prognosis</strong></p>



<p>Despite the new diagnostic and genetic technologies that are now available and the many advances in surgical technique and biologic treatment, such as targeted treatment and immunotherapy, the overall 5-year survival rate of lung cancer in the world today is worse than before. Most lung cancer is discovered at an advanced stage, and the fact that only 15% of lung cancers are discovered in early stages may be responsible for the dismal prognosis. Therefore, early diagnosis by screening high-risk populations using low-dose computed tomography scan and effective biomarkers may improve the survival of lung cancer patients.</p>



<p><strong>Prevention of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>In the prevention of lung cancer, there is no sure way but one can help reduce its risk if:</p>



<p><strong>Avoid Smoking:</strong>&nbsp;For individuals who haven’t smoked, it is safe to avoid smoking at all cost being the major cause of lung cancer. And for people who smoke, one needs to quit smoking. Avoid areas where people smoke such as bars and restaurants, and seek out smoke free areas.</p>



<p><strong>Preventing Air Pollution:</strong>&nbsp;This is done by reducing carbon emission using clean energy such as electric cars, solar power etc.</p>



<p><strong>Radon Level Check:</strong>&nbsp;For individuals who live where uranium are usually found, it is safe to have one’s home checked for radon levels. High radon levels can be remedied to make home safer.</p>



<p><strong>Avoid Carcinogens at Work:</strong>&nbsp;Taking safety precautions from toxic exposure at work is good. This can include using of a face mask for protection if provided with one at the office. The risk of lung damages from workplace carcinogens increases of an individual smokes.</p>



<p><strong>Eating Diets Filled with Fruits and Vegetables:</strong>&nbsp;Choosing a healthy diet with a variety of fruits and vegetables is good for the body. Avoid taking large doses of vitamins in pill form, as some might be harmful.</p>



<p><strong>Engage in Healthy Physical Activity:</strong>&nbsp;Exercising regularly and other physical activity can help reduce the risk associated with lung cancer.</p>



<p><strong>N.B:</strong>&nbsp;Data for current world statistics on lung cancer among men, women and both sexes can be gotten from&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wcrf.org/int/cancer-facts-figures/data-specific-cancers/lung-cancer-statistics%20">https://www.wcrf.org/int/cancer-facts-figures/data-specific-cancers/lung-cancer-statistics%20</a></p>



<p><strong><em>[Next&nbsp;Article on Lung Cancer&nbsp;– How Lung Cancer Presents Clinically]</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/epidemiology-and-prevention-of-lung-cancer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>INFECTIOUS HEPATITIS (Hepatitis A and Hepatitis E)</title>
		<link>/infectious-hepatitis-hepatitis-a-and-hepatitis-e/</link>
					<comments>/infectious-hepatitis-hepatitis-a-and-hepatitis-e/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10627</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hepatitis can be referred to as an inflammatory disease or conditions that affect mostly the liver. Hepatitis can be referred to as an inflammatory disease or conditions that affect mostly the liver. It is usually caused by a viral infection, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Infectious-Hepatitis.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10628"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Hepatitis can be referred to as an inflammatory disease or conditions that affect mostly the liver.</p>
</div></div>



<p>Hepatitis can be referred to as an inflammatory disease or conditions that affect mostly the liver. It is usually caused by a viral infection, yet there are other causes which may include autoimmune hepatitis and secondary hepatitis complications (this is usually caused by drugs, toxics and alcohol). Autoimmune hepatitis occurs as when diseases make the human body antibodies against liver tissues.</p>



<p>Infectious Hepatitis, unlike other viral hepatitis usually occurs through contamination of food, water or other edible things by the faeces of an infected person. This type of hepatitis is of two types i.e. Hepatitis A and Hepatitis E.</p>



<p>Hepatitis A is caused by an infection with the hepatitis A virus (HAV); and is commonly transmitted by consuming food or water contaminated by faeces from another person with hepatitis A. Hepatitis E on the other hand is a waterborne disease caused by the hepatitis E virus (HEV), and mostly found in geographical areas with poor sanitation (especially in the less developing world). Like Hepatitis A, it is transmitted in consuming contaminated water or food.</p>



<p><strong>Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p>Hepatitis A is a highly contagious liver infection that is caused by the hepatitis A virus (HAV). It is one of the different types of hepatitis viruses that cause inflammation and thus affecting the liver from functioning appropriately. It is primarily spread when an uninfected and unvaccinated person consume food or water that had already been contaminated with the faeces of an infected person. This virus infectious disease is usually linked to unsafe water, food, poor hygiene and environmental sanitation, and the anal-oral sex among human being.</p>



<p>It can be mild or severe dependent on if the affected person has been vaccinated or not, or if there aren’t cases of other form of chronic diseases in the body. Whenever an individual has a mild case of hepatitis A, it usually don’t require any form of treatment; thus making it possible to recover completely from such diseases.</p>



<p>Hepatitis A, unlike other types of hepatitis such as B and C, doesn’t cause chronic liver disease and isn’t fatal, yet it can cause debilitating symptoms and acute liver failure. The best way to be protected against hepatitis A is the practice of good hygiene, including washing of hands frequently; and also getting vaccinated against hepatitis A.</p>



<p>Globally, hepatitis A usually occurs occasionally or in intervals and in epidemic, with the tendency of certain recurrences (especially in cases of foodborne infection). This can lead to significant socio-economic breakdown, causing people who have been infected to recover after several weeks or month to their various daily lives.</p>



<p>In 2016, the World Health Organisation (WHO) estimated that a total number of 7,134 persons died from the hepatitis A infection globally; thus accounting for only 0.5% of the mortality due to viral hepatitis.</p>



<p><strong>Transmission of Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p>Hepatitis A virus is mainly transmitted through faeces, thus when an uninfected person digest or consume food or water that has been contaminated with the faeces of an infected person. Also, whenever an infected person prepares food with his/her dirty hands, there is a high chance of transmission to other persons who eats the food. Waterborne outbreaks, through infrequent, are usually associated with sewage-contaminated or inadequately treated water.</p>



<p>Also, the virus can also be transmitted through close physical contact i.e. sexually with an infected person (through oral-anal sex). Other form of casual physical contact among people does not spread the virus among individuals.</p>



<p><strong>Geographical Distribution of Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p>According to World Health Organisation (WHO) data collection team, Hepatitis A geographical distribution areas can be characterized as having high, intermediate or low levels of hepatitis A virus infection. However, infection does not mean disease because children infected young do not experience any noticeable symptoms.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Areas with High Levels of Infection</strong></li></ul>



<p>In low- and middle-income countries with poor sanitary conditions and hygienic practices, infection is common and most children (90%) have been infected with the hepatitis A virus before the age of 10 years, most often without symptoms. Epidemics are uncommon because older children and adults are generally immune. Symptomatic disease rates in these areas are low and outbreaks are rare.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Areas with Low Levels of Infection</strong></li></ul>



<p>In high-income countries with good sanitary and hygienic conditions, infection rates are low. Disease may occur among adolescents and adults in high-risk groups, such as PWIDs, MSMs, people travelling to areas of high endemicity, and in isolated populations, such as closed religious groups.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Areas with Intermediate Levels of Infection</strong></li></ul>



<p>In middle-income countries, and regions where sanitary conditions are variable, children often escape infection in early childhood and reach adulthood without immunity. Ironically, these improved economic and sanitary conditions may lead to accumulation of adults who have never been infected and who have no immunity. This higher susceptibility in older age groups may lead to higher disease rates and large outbreaks can occur in these communities.</p>



<p><strong>Symptoms of Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p>Typically, whenever an individual is infected with the Hepatitis A disease, signs and symptoms don’t usually surface until some weeks after infection. Sometimes it can also be asymptomatic i.e. not showing any sign or symptoms in the human body.</p>



<p>Symptoms of Hepatitis A can grow from mild (i.e. it tends to go away after some weeks) to severe (severe illness that might last up to months), and they include:</p>



<ul><li>Fatigue</li><li>Sudden nausea and vomiting</li><li>Abdominal pain or discomfort, especially on the upper right side beneath your lower ribs (by your liver)</li><li>Clay-colored bowel movements</li><li>Loss of appetite</li><li>Low-grade fever</li><li>Dark urine</li><li>Joint pain</li><li>Yellowing of the skin and the whites of your eyes (jaundice)</li><li>Intense itching</li></ul>



<p>Adults have signs and symptoms of illness more often than children. The severity of disease and fatal outcomes are higher in older age groups. Infected children under 6 years of age do not usually experience noticeable symptoms, ad only 10% develop jaundice. Among older children and adults, infection usually causes more severe symptoms, with jaundice occurring in more than 70% of cases; and sometimes cases of Hepatitis A may relapse.</p>



<p><strong>Treatment and Prevention of Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p><strong>Treatment of Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p>At the moment, there is no existing treatment for hepatitis A. The human body can clear the hepatitis A virus on its own, and keeping a healthy hygiene system helps. Also, the following could help:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Rest:</strong>&nbsp;Whenever an individual is infected with the hepatitis A infection, there is a need to properly rest and save energy because there is always the feeling of being tired and sick, and thus losing energy.</li><li><strong>Nausea Management:</strong>&nbsp;Having nausea can cause a lot of difficulty like loss of appetite, drowsiness etc. Eating food with high calories, juice or milk is more advisable than water. Drinking plenty of fluids is important to prevent dehydration if vomiting occurs.</li><li><strong>Alcohol Intake:</strong>&nbsp;In case of hepatitis A, it is advisable to avoid all sort of alcohol intake as they tend to cause more liver damage.</li><li><strong>Avoid Sexual Activity:</strong>&nbsp;Persons with hepatitis A should avoid all sexual activity. Having sex during infection can spread the infection to one’s partner as condoms don’t offer adequate protection.</li><li><strong>Washing of Hands:</strong>&nbsp;Keeping safe hygiene like washing of hands after the use of toilet is quite important. Infection can easily be passed to others if food is prepared if hands are not properly washed.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Prevention of Hepatitis A</strong></p>



<p>Hepatitis A can only be prevented through improved sanitation, food safety and immunization through the hepatitis A vaccine which is available globally. The vaccine helps to protect the human body from the virus and thus have no side effects. Spreading of hepatitis A can only be reduced by:</p>



<ul><li>Adequate supplies of safe drinking water</li><li>Proper disposal of sewage within communities</li><li>Personal hygienic practices such as regular hand – washing before meals and after using the toilets</li></ul>



<p><strong><em>[Next Article on Infectious Hepatitis: Hepatitis E]</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/infectious-hepatitis-hepatitis-a-and-hepatitis-e/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>LUNG CANCER: OVERVIEW AND INTRODUCTION</title>
		<link>/lung-cancer-overview-and-introduction/</link>
					<comments>/lung-cancer-overview-and-introduction/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 15:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10630</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lung cancer, just like every other type of cancer is an abnormality that begins from the lung. It is one of the most common cancer that affects both the male and female sexes. Lung cancer is the leading form of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Lungs-cancer.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10631"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Lung cancer, just like every other type of cancer is an abnormality that begins from the lung. It is one of the most common cancer that affects both the male and female sexes.</p>
</div></div>



<p>Lung cancer is the leading form of cancer and leading cause of cancer death in the world today; where there is an approximate number of 1.8 million cases diagnosed every year with 70% in developing countries. It is a type of cancer that begins when abnormal cells start to grow in one of or both lungs in the human body, causing the growth of tumors that reduces one’s inability to breathe. It is a common prevailing form of cancer that happens to both men and women.</p>



<p>The moment the lung cancer starts from the lung itself, it is medically referred to as Primary Lung Cancer. It can spread to other parts of the body like the lymph nodes, brain, adrenal glands, bones and liver. But if diagnosed early, the rate of spreading to other part of the body is minimal.</p>



<p>When cancer from other part of the body like the breasts, liver, pancreatic and colon, spreads to the lung, it is called secondary or metastatic cancer in the lung.</p>



<p>Lung cancer is one of the most avoidable forms of cancer due to one of its risk factors i.e. smoking. Yet that shouldn’t undermine other causes like the radon exposure.</p>



<p>Presently in the world today, the death rate associated with lung cancer has significantly dropped over the years, 51% among men and 26% among women. And this is due to the significant breakthrough in scientific research on lung cancer and its prevention.</p>



<p>As earlier stated, lung cancer is characterized by the uncontrolled growth of abnormal cells in one or both of the lungs, thus the majority of lung cancers begin in the bronchial tubes (i.e. the pinkish gray walls of the lungs airway) or air sacs that conduct air in and out of the lungs. Most cancers of the lung are classified by how they appear under a microscope.</p>



<p><strong>The Lung</strong></p>



<p>The lungs are two sponge-like organs in the chest which is the main organ for breathing, and are part of the respiratory system. As well as the lungs, the respiratory system includes the nose, mouth, trachea (windpipe), and airways (tubes) to each lung. There are large airways known as bronchi (singular: bronchus). Whenever individuals breathe in (inhale), air goes into the nose or mouth, down the trachea and into the bronchi and bronchioles. At the end of the bronchioles, tiny air sacs called&nbsp;alveoli&nbsp;pass oxygen into the blood and collect the waste gas (carbon dioxide). When one breathes out (exhale), carbon dioxide is removed from the body and released back into the atmosphere.</p>



<p>Each lung is made up of sections called lobes – the left lung has two lobes which are due to the room the heart occupies, and the right lung has three.</p>



<p><strong>Lung Cancer in Nigeria</strong></p>



<p>In Nigeria, lung cancer is one of the most diagnosed forms of cancer among men and women, after prostate and breast respectively. Lung cancer alone is responsible for over 100 thousand cases in the country and this might be due to the increase in first and second chain smoking amidst people.</p>



<p>From a study taken by the University Teaching Hospital (UCH), Ibadan in 2018; it was discovered that the ratio prevalence of lung cancer among both sexes is 1.8:1 (male: female) after 1347 cases were discovered with 1262 death cases recorded, with a cumulative risk percentage at 0.78. This might have been caused by cases of tobacco smoking prevalent in rural areas due to lack of proper sensitization.</p>



<p><strong>Types of Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>There are two primary types of lung cancer, i.e. non-small cell lung cancer and small cell lung cancer.</p>



<ol><li><strong>Non &#8211; Small Cell Lung Cancer</strong></li></ol>



<p>&nbsp;This is the most common type of lung cancer that has been known to responsible for 80% &#8211; 85% of lung cancer cases. It is common among women, people who are second-chain or non-smokers and youths.</p>



<p>The non-small cell lung cancer can be further classed into three types:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Lung Adenocarcinoma:</strong>&nbsp;Lung adenocarcinoma is a type of non-small lung cancers that has been responsible for almost half of these cases, and also currently the most common type of lung cancer. It is common among former and current smokers, also common among non-smokers too. This type is usually found in the deeper part of the lungs; this is because most smoke from filtered cigarette or tobacco inhaled settles there. It is usually common among women, young adults than men.</li><li><strong>Large Cell (Undifferentiated) Lung Cancer:</strong>&nbsp;The large cell carcinomas of the lungs tend to grow in the outer part of the lungs. They are the fast growing tumors that tend to spread quickly and also to other parts of the body.</li><li><strong>Squamous Cell Carcinoma:</strong>&nbsp;Squamous cell cancers are the type of lung cancer that occurs in or near the large airways of the lung. This is because the airways are usually the part of the lungs that is exposed to smoke from cigarette or tobacco. It was once known as the most common type of lung cancer before most cigarette makers added filters to their products.</li></ul>



<p><strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Small Cell Lung Cancer</strong></p>



<p>This type of lung cancer is responsible for about 10% &#8211; 15% of all lung cancers. It tends to grow and spread faster than the non-small cell lung cancer. About 70% of people with small cell lung cancer will have the cancer to have spread at the time they are diagnosed; this is because it tends to be aggressive and not easily found until spread, especially to the brain.</p>



<p>Due to its nature of spreading easily and quickly, they usually tend to respond fairly well to chemotherapy and radiation therapy but have a poor prognosis i.e. it may return at some point in time.</p>



<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>



<p>Along with the main types of lung cancer, other tumors can also occur in the lungs, and they include carcinoid tumor, neuroendocrine tumors, lymphomas, sarcomas, and also benign lung tumors such as hamartomas.</p>



<p>These tumors are quite rare, especially the carcinoid tumor of the lung which only occur among less than 5% of lung tumors.</p>



<p><strong><em>[Next Article on Lung Cancer: Epidemiology and Prevention]</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/lung-cancer-overview-and-introduction/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WHO Intensifies Efforts to Support Lassa Fever Response in West Africa</title>
		<link>/who-intensifies-efforts-to-support-lassa-fever-response-in-west-africa/</link>
					<comments>/who-intensifies-efforts-to-support-lassa-fever-response-in-west-africa/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 16:21:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10603</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The World Health Organization, (WHO), Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to support West African Countries in their response to the ongoing Lassa Fever Outbreak. The World Health Organization, (WHO), on Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/WHO.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10604"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">The World Health Organization, (WHO), Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to support West African Countries in their response to the ongoing Lassa Fever Outbreak.</p>
</div></div>



<p>The World Health Organization, (WHO), on Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to support West African Countries in their response to the ongoing Lassa Fever Outbreak.</p>



<p>Collins Boakye-Agyemang, WHO‘s communications Manager made this known in a statement. He said that while the outbreak was fairly prevalent during the Lassa fever season, the rate of escalation was a major concern in most areas.</p>



<p>In his statement, he said that in Nigeria alone, 16 states were affected; about 213 cases were confirmed; including 42 deaths, which represented a significant increase.</p>



<p>According to him, Nigeria recorded its largest outbreak of Lassa fever with four health workers reported to have been infected so far in this current outbreak.</p>



<p>He, however, noted that WHO is intensifying efforts to support federal authorities, the Nigeria Center for Disease control, and the affected Nigerian States, in staging a response to the outbreak. He said that focus is shifting towards early detection and confirmation of suspected cases.</p>



<p>He also said that and providing adequate supportive care, ensuring infection prevention and control measures, in designated health care centers in the affected states were also top on their agenda.</p>



<p>&nbsp;12 cases have so far been confirmed in Benin, Guinea, Liberia and Togo, including two deaths, with more suspected cases currently undergoing investigation.</p>



<p>”Health authorities in these countries are beign assisted with contact tracing, provision of medical and non-medical supplies with technical and financial resources as needed for case management, risk communication and logistics.</p>



<p>”We are concerned by the high number of cases so early in the Lassa fever season, which is expected to last another four more months.</p>



<p>“WHO is working with health authorities in the five affected countries and will ensure that health workers have the capacity to detect cases and regional spread of the disease was monitored, “he said.</p>



<p>He added that WHO has provided regional control mechanism for countries to reported cases of the Lassa fever disease. This is to aid information flow and assistance coordination.</p>



<p>‘‘WHO will continue to advise all countries in the Lassa fever belt, to enhance their preparedness and response capacities.</p>



<p>“Especially for early case detection, laboratory confirmation, case management under recommended barrier nursing, risk communication and community engagement.</p>



<p>“Lassa fever is an acute viral haemorrhagic illness that occurs predominantly in West Africa, after human exposure to the urine or faeces of infected Mastomys rats.</p>



<p>”More than 80 percent of Lassa fever cases are rodent-to-human transmission. Person-to-person transmission, occurs in both community and health-care settings.”Prevention of Lassa fever is based on promoting good “community hygiene,” to discourage rodents from entering homes.</p>



<p>“It could also be by storing grain and other foodstuffs in rodent-proof containers, disposing of garbage far from the home.” Also maintaining clean households, keeping cats and safe handling of anyone who may have died of the disease.</p>



<p>”In health care settings, health care workers should always apply standard infection prevention and control precautions when caring for patients,” he said.</p>



<p><strong><em>World Health Organization</em></strong></p>



<p><strong><em>Guardian Health Column</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/who-intensifies-efforts-to-support-lassa-fever-response-in-west-africa/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Management of Colorectal Cancer II: Causes, Risk Factors and Prevention</title>
		<link>/management-of-colorectal-cancer-ii-causes-risk-factors-and-prevention/</link>
					<comments>/management-of-colorectal-cancer-ii-causes-risk-factors-and-prevention/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 12:16:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10633</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Causes of colorectal cancer depend on the both the non &#8211; avoidable and avoidable reason. Causes of Colorectal Cancer Medical doctors and researchers are not certain about the main cause of most colorectal cancers, yet there are several risk factors [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/colon-cancer.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10634"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Causes of colorectal cancer depend on the both the non &#8211; avoidable and avoidable reason.</p>
</div></div>



<p><strong>Causes of Colorectal Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Medical doctors and researchers are not certain about the main cause of most colorectal cancers, yet there are several risk factors that can increase an individual’s risk of colorectal cancer, but it’s not exactly clear how all these factors might cause colorectal cancer. Generally, colon cancer begins when healthy cells in the colon and rectum develop changes (mutations) in their DNA.</p>



<p><strong>Precancerous Growths:&nbsp;</strong>Abnormal cells accumulate in the lining of the colon, forming&nbsp;polyps. These are small, benign growths. Removing these growths through surgery is a common preventive method. Untreated polyps can become cancerous.</p>



<p><strong>Gene Mutations:</strong>&nbsp;Sometimes colorectal cancer occurs in family members. This is due to a gene mutation that passes from parent to child. These mutations don’t guarantee that an individual would develop colorectal cancer, but they do increase the chances.</p>



<p><strong>Risk Factors of Colorectal Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Just as explained earlier, there are several factors that increase the risk of colorectal cancer in an individual, and these factors can be divided into two:</p>



<ol><li><strong>Unavoidable Factors</strong></li></ol>



<p>Some factors that increase risk of developing colorectal cancer are unavoidable and can’t be changed.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Age:</strong>&nbsp;This risk of colorectal cancer increases as an individual get older, it can be diagnosed at any age, but most individuals with colon cancer are older than 50. For colon cancer, the average age at the time of diagnosis for men is 68 and for women are 72. For rectal cancer, it is age 63 for both men and women.</li><li><strong>Race and Ethnic Background:&nbsp;</strong>Jews and Blacks i.e. (African Americans and Africans) are more vulnerable when it comes to colorectal cancer incidence and mortality rates among all racial groups in the world.</li><li><strong>Personal History of Colorectal Cancer of Colorectal Polyps:</strong>&nbsp;If an individual had already had colorectal cancer or noncancerous colon polyps, even if it was completely removed; he / she is more likely to develop cancer in other parts of the colon and rectum in the future.</li><li><strong>Family History of Colon Cancer:</strong>&nbsp;Individuals who have a family history of colorectal cancer especially from first – degree relatives (i.e. parents, brothers, sisters, grandparents etc.), have a risk of developing colorectal cancer in the nearest future.</li></ul>



<p>The risk further increases if other close relatives have also developed colorectal cancer or if a first-degree relative was diagnosed at a younger age.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Rare Inherited Conditions:</strong>&nbsp;Some gene mutations passed through generations of an individual’s family can increase the risk of colon cancer significantly. Only a small percentage of colon cancers are linked to inherited genes. The most common inherited syndromes that increase colon cancer risk are familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP) and Lynch syndrome, which is also known as hereditary nonpolyposis colorectal cancer (HNPCC).</li><li><strong>Inflammatory Bowel Conditions:</strong>&nbsp;Chronic inflammatory diseases of the colon, such as ulcerative colitis and Crohn&#8217;s disease can increase the risk of colon cancer.</li><li><strong>Adenomatous Polyps (Adenomas).</strong>&nbsp;Polyps are not cancer, but some types of polyps called adenomas can develop into colorectal cancer over time. Polyps removal can prevent colorectal cancer. People who have had adenomas have a greater risk of additional polyps and of colorectal cancer, and they should have follow-up screening tests regularly.</li></ul>



<p><strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp; Avoidable Factors</strong></p>



<p>Other risk factors are avoidable. This means an individual can change them to decrease the risk of developing colorectal cancer. Many lifestyle-related factors have been linked to colorectal cancer. In fact, the links between diet, weight, and exercise and colorectal cancer risk are some of the strongest for any type of cancer. Avoidable risk factors include:</p>



<ul><li><strong>Obesity (Being Overweight):</strong>&nbsp;People who are obese have an increased risk of colon cancer and an increased risk of dying of colorectal cancer when compared with people considered normal weight. Being overweight (especially having a larger waistline) raises the risk of colon and rectal cancer in both men and women, but the link seems to be stronger in men.</li><li><strong>Physical Inactivity:</strong>&nbsp;People who are inactive (don’t exercise) are more likely to develop colorectal cancer. Involving in regular physical activities may reduce the risk of colorectal cancer.</li><li><strong>Certain Types of Diets:</strong>&nbsp;Diets that are high in red meats i.e. beef, pork, lamb and processed meats like hotdogs can raise the risk of colorectal cancer.</li><li><strong>Smoking:</strong>&nbsp;People who smoke are more likely to develop and die from colorectal cancer, especially since smoking is known to be the main cause of lung cancer.</li><li><strong>Alcohol:</strong>&nbsp;People who tend to drink alcohol moderately or heavily tend to develop colorectal cancer.</li></ul>



<ul><li><strong>Type 2 Diabetes Patients:</strong>&nbsp;Individuals with type 2 diabetes or insulin resistance have an increased risk of colon cancer. Both type 2 diabetes and colorectal cancer share some of the same risk factors (such as being overweight and physical inactivity), yet they have a higher and increased risk.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Prevention of Colorectal Cancer</strong></p>



<p>Certain risk factors for colorectal cancer, such as family history and age, aren’t preventable. However, lifestyle factors that may contribute colorectal cancer&nbsp;<em>are&nbsp;</em>preventable, and may help reduce the overall risk of developing this disease.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Colorectal Cancer Screening:</strong>&nbsp;Getting screened can help to discover colorectal cancer in individuals with no symptoms of the disease. Regularly going for colorectal screening is the best way of preventing colorectal cancer. Doctors recommend that people with an average risk of colon cancer should consider colon cancer screening around age 50. But people with an increased risk, such as those with a family history of colon cancer, should consider screening sooner.</li><li><strong>Aspirin and other Non-steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs):&nbsp;</strong>Some studies suggest that aspirin and other NSAIDs may reduce the development of polyps in people with a history of colorectal cancer or polyps. However, regular use of NSAIDs may cause major side effects, including bleeding of the stomach lining and blood clots leading to stroke or heart attack.&nbsp;</li><li><strong>Diets and Supplements</strong>:&nbsp;Limiting red and processed meats and eating more vegetables and fruits may help lower risk of colorectal cancer. Fruits, vegetables and whole grains contain vitamins, minerals, fiber and antioxidants, which may play a role in colorectal cancer prevention. In recent years, some large studies have suggested that fiber in the diet, especially from whole grains, may lower colorectal cancer risk. Also, people who take calcium and vitamin D supplements have a lower risk of colorectal cancer.</li><li><strong>Alcohol Intake:</strong>&nbsp;Excessive alcohol intake has been known to be a risk factor for colorectal cancer; limiting the intake of alcohol can help to reduce the risk of colorectal cancer in any individual.</li><li><strong>Quit Smoking:</strong>&nbsp;Long-term smoking is linked to an increased risk of colorectal cancer, as well as many other cancers and health problems.Quitting smoking may help lower the risk of colorectal cancer and many other types of cancer, too.</li><li><strong>Physical Activity:</strong>&nbsp;Keeping fit and getting involved in physical activity can help to lower the risk of colorectal cancer and polyps.</li><li><strong>Maintaining a Healthy Weight:</strong>&nbsp;It is important for individuals with family history of obesity to maintain a healthy weight i.e. work to maintain their weight. There should be aim to lose weight slowly by increasing the amount of exercise one get and reducing the number of calories one eat.</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/management-of-colorectal-cancer-ii-causes-risk-factors-and-prevention/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Management of Hepatitis C I: Investigation and Treatment</title>
		<link>/management-of-hepatitis-c-i-investigation-and-treatment/</link>
					<comments>/management-of-hepatitis-c-i-investigation-and-treatment/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:08:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10636</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Medical doctors recommend that adults aged between18 to 79 years be screened for hepatitis C, even those without symptoms or known liver disease. Management of Hepatitis C I: Investigation and Treatment Investigation of Hepatitis C When it comes to hepatitis [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Hepatitis-C.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10637"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Medical doctors recommend that adults aged between18 to 79 years be screened for hepatitis C, even those without symptoms or known liver disease.</p>
</div></div>



<p><strong>Management of Hepatitis C I: Investigation and Treatment</strong></p>



<p><strong>Investigation of Hepatitis C</strong></p>



<p>When it comes to hepatitis C, most patients (60 to 70 percent) with HCV infection are asymptomatic i.e. they don’t show any sign or symptom; when symptoms do occur, they are non-specific and include fatigue, nausea, anorexia, myalgias, arthralgias, weakness, and weight loss. This sometimes makes it difficult for most medical doctors to ascertain what could be physically wrong with an individual.</p>



<p>This is the reason why it is important to investigate certain symptoms by seeking counsel and visiting a hospital for diagnosis. This is the reason why medical doctors recommend that adults aged between18 to 79 years be screened for hepatitis C, even those without symptoms or known liver disease. Screening for&nbsp;HCV&nbsp;is especially important if one is at high risk of exposure, including:</p>



<ul><li>Individual who have injected or inhaled illicit / illegal drugs.</li><li>Individual who have abnormal liver function test results with no identified cause.</li><li>Babies born to mothers with hepatitis C.</li><li>Health care workers who might have been exposed to blood or used and contaminated injections / syringe.</li><li>People with hemophilia and might have undergone long – term hemodialysis treatments.</li><li>People who received blood transfusions illegally.</li><li>Sexual partners of anyone diagnosed with hepatitis C infection.</li><li>People with HIV infection.</li><li>Anyone who has been in prison and might have gotten involved with other people with the HCV.</li></ul>



<p>Also, medical doctors could also recommend the test of liver so as to locate any form of abnormalities; and this happen when hepatitis C might have become chronic in the body. Doctors typically use one or more of the following tests to assess liver damage in chronic hepatitis C.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Magnetic Resonance Elastography (MRE):</strong>&nbsp;A noninvasive alternative to a liver biopsy,&nbsp;MRE&nbsp;combines magnetic resonance imaging technology with patterns formed by sound waves bouncing off the liver to create a visual map showing gradients of stiffness throughout the liver. Stiff liver tissue indicates the presence of scarring of the liver (fibrosis) as a result of chronic hepatitis C.</li><li><strong>Transient Elastography:</strong>&nbsp;Another noninvasive test, transient elastography is a type of ultrasound that transmits vibrations into the liver and measures the speed of their dispersal through liver tissue to estimate its stiffness.</li><li><strong>Liver Biopsy:</strong>&nbsp;Typically done using ultrasound guidance, this test involves inserting a thin needle through the abdominal wall to remove a small sample of liver tissue for laboratory testing.</li><li><strong>Blood Tests:</strong>&nbsp;A series of blood tests can indicate the extent of fibrosis in the liver.Although hepatitis C virus has no form of vaccine at the moment, yet certain medicine can be used to curb its effect on different individuals.</li></ul>



<p><strong>Treatment of Hepatitis C</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Antiviral medications</strong></li></ul>



<p>Hepatitis C infection is treated with antiviral medications intended to clear the virus from the body. The goal of treatment is to have no hepatitis C virus detected in the body at least 12 weeks after a complete treatment.</p>



<p>Medical researchers have recently made significant advances in treatment for hepatitis C using new, direct-acting antiviral (DAA) medications.</p>



<p>These DAA has been known to be the safest and most effective medicines for treating hepatitis C. The choice of medications and length of treatment depend on the hepatitis C genotype, presence of existing liver damage, other medical conditions and prior treatments. Some types of hepatitis C can be treated using more than 1 type of DAA.</p>



<p>Some of the approved hepatitis C medicines include:</p>



<ol><li>Simeprevir</li><li>Sofosbuvir</li><li>A combination of ledipasvir and sofosbuvir</li><li>A combination of ombitasvir, paritaprevir and ritonavir, taken with or without dasabuvir</li><li>A combination of sofosbuvir and velpatasvir</li><li>A combination of sofosbuvir, velpatasvir and voxilaprevir</li><li>A combination of glecaprevir and pibrentasvir</li><li>Ribavarin</li></ol>



<ul><li><strong>Liver Transplantation</strong></li></ul>



<p>For individuals who might have developed serious complications from chronic hepatitis C infection, liver transplant might be an option for them. This is because there might be need for their damaged livers to be replaced with healthy ones.</p>



<p>In most cases, a liver transplant alone doesn&#8217;t cure hepatitis C. The infection is likely to return, requiring treatment with antiviral medication to prevent damage to the transplanted liver. Several studies have demonstrated that new, direct-acting antiviral medication regimens are effective at curing post-transplant hepatitis C. At the same time, treatment with direct-acting antivirals can be achieved in appropriately selected patients before liver transplantation.</p>



<ul><li><strong>Vaccinations</strong></li></ul>



<p>Although there is no vaccine for hepatitis C, doctors are more likely to recommend that an individual receive vaccines against the hepatitis A and B viruses. These are separate viruses that also can cause liver damage and complicate the course of chronic hepatitis C.</p>



<p><strong><em>[Next Article: Causes and Prevention of Hepatitis C]</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/management-of-hepatitis-c-i-investigation-and-treatment/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
