<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>DISEASES &#8211; Medical Tutors</title>
	<atom:link href="/all-news/diseases/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>E-Learning for Medical Experts</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 13:35:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.4.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/cropped-Medicaltutors-03-32x32.png</url>
	<title>DISEASES &#8211; Medical Tutors</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>WHO Intensifies Efforts to Support Lassa Fever Response in West Africa</title>
		<link>/who-intensifies-efforts-to-support-lassa-fever-response-in-west-africa/</link>
					<comments>/who-intensifies-efforts-to-support-lassa-fever-response-in-west-africa/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 16:21:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10603</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The World Health Organization, (WHO), Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to support West African Countries in their response to the ongoing Lassa Fever Outbreak. The World Health Organization, (WHO), on Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/WHO.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10604"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">The World Health Organization, (WHO), Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to support West African Countries in their response to the ongoing Lassa Fever Outbreak.</p>
</div></div>



<p>The World Health Organization, (WHO), on Sunday, announced its decision to intensify efforts to support West African Countries in their response to the ongoing Lassa Fever Outbreak.</p>



<p>Collins Boakye-Agyemang, WHO‘s communications Manager made this known in a statement. He said that while the outbreak was fairly prevalent during the Lassa fever season, the rate of escalation was a major concern in most areas.</p>



<p>In his statement, he said that in Nigeria alone, 16 states were affected; about 213 cases were confirmed; including 42 deaths, which represented a significant increase.</p>



<p>According to him, Nigeria recorded its largest outbreak of Lassa fever with four health workers reported to have been infected so far in this current outbreak.</p>



<p>He, however, noted that WHO is intensifying efforts to support federal authorities, the Nigeria Center for Disease control, and the affected Nigerian States, in staging a response to the outbreak. He said that focus is shifting towards early detection and confirmation of suspected cases.</p>



<p>He also said that and providing adequate supportive care, ensuring infection prevention and control measures, in designated health care centers in the affected states were also top on their agenda.</p>



<p>&nbsp;12 cases have so far been confirmed in Benin, Guinea, Liberia and Togo, including two deaths, with more suspected cases currently undergoing investigation.</p>



<p>”Health authorities in these countries are beign assisted with contact tracing, provision of medical and non-medical supplies with technical and financial resources as needed for case management, risk communication and logistics.</p>



<p>”We are concerned by the high number of cases so early in the Lassa fever season, which is expected to last another four more months.</p>



<p>“WHO is working with health authorities in the five affected countries and will ensure that health workers have the capacity to detect cases and regional spread of the disease was monitored, “he said.</p>



<p>He added that WHO has provided regional control mechanism for countries to reported cases of the Lassa fever disease. This is to aid information flow and assistance coordination.</p>



<p>‘‘WHO will continue to advise all countries in the Lassa fever belt, to enhance their preparedness and response capacities.</p>



<p>“Especially for early case detection, laboratory confirmation, case management under recommended barrier nursing, risk communication and community engagement.</p>



<p>“Lassa fever is an acute viral haemorrhagic illness that occurs predominantly in West Africa, after human exposure to the urine or faeces of infected Mastomys rats.</p>



<p>”More than 80 percent of Lassa fever cases are rodent-to-human transmission. Person-to-person transmission, occurs in both community and health-care settings.”Prevention of Lassa fever is based on promoting good “community hygiene,” to discourage rodents from entering homes.</p>



<p>“It could also be by storing grain and other foodstuffs in rodent-proof containers, disposing of garbage far from the home.” Also maintaining clean households, keeping cats and safe handling of anyone who may have died of the disease.</p>



<p>”In health care settings, health care workers should always apply standard infection prevention and control precautions when caring for patients,” he said.</p>



<p><strong><em>World Health Organization</em></strong></p>



<p><strong><em>Guardian Health Column</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/who-intensifies-efforts-to-support-lassa-fever-response-in-west-africa/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cholera Outbreak In Borno Takes New Twist</title>
		<link>/cholera-outbreak-in-borno-takes-new-twist/</link>
					<comments>/cholera-outbreak-in-borno-takes-new-twist/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 16:17:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10600</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[14 people had previously died in the affected areas before the outbreak was announced officially. The ongoing Cholera Outbreak in Borno State which was declared Wednesday Last Week has taken a new turn. According to a statement released by the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/cholera-borno.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10601"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">14 people had previously died in the affected areas before the outbreak was announced officially.</p>
</div></div>



<p>The ongoing Cholera Outbreak in Borno State which was declared Wednesday Last Week has taken a new turn.</p>



<p>According to a statement released by the State Commissioner of Health, Dr. Haruna Mshelia, the outbreak was declared after eight samples sent to the laboratory for testing proved positive.</p>



<p>However, his report also highlighted that 14 people had previously died in the same areas where acute diarrhoea was diagnosed, but he could not confirm if their deaths were as a result of Cholera as no autopsy was carried out.</p>



<p>He said, “With the Laboratory confirmation of samples of eight suspected cholera cases sent to NCDC laboratory in Abuja, the Borno State Ministry of Health Officially declares an Outbreak.”</p>



<p>Suspected cases had also been reported from several areas of the State, including Kaga with 28 cases, Konduga with 36 cases, Magumeri with 139 cases, Old Maiduguri with 67 cases and Chibok with 78 cases.</p>



<p>A full-scale emergency operations response for a concerted response to the outbreak has since been activated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cholera-outbreak-in-borno-takes-new-twist/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Government of Delta State has confirmed the death of a 75-year-old woman as a result of Lassa Fever.</title>
		<link>/the-government-of-delta-state-has-confirmed-the-death-of-a-75-year-old-woman-as-a-result-of-lassa-fever/</link>
					<comments>/the-government-of-delta-state-has-confirmed-the-death-of-a-75-year-old-woman-as-a-result-of-lassa-fever/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 16:15:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10597</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Government of Delta State has confirmed the death of a 75-year-old woman as a result of Lassa Fever. The Government of Delta State has confirmed the death of a 75-year-old woman as a result of Lassa Fever. The State [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/delta.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10598"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">The Government of Delta State has confirmed the death of a 75-year-old woman as a result of Lassa Fever.</p>
</div></div>



<p>The Government of Delta State has confirmed the death of a 75-year-old woman as a result of Lassa Fever.</p>



<p>The State Government in a statement signed by the Director of information, Paul Osahor, said the incident occurred after the woman fell ill and went to the General Hospital, Umuolu, Ndokwa East Local Government Area (LGA) on Saturday, August 18, 2018.</p>



<p>She was then transferred to the Central Hospital, Kwale, Ndokwa West LGA the following day, August 19<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;and from there was further referred to the Federal Medical Centre (FMC), Asaba on August 24, 2018.</p>



<p>While at FMC, Asaba, the victim’s blood sample was taken to Irrua Specialist Hospital, Edo State for a test but she died on August 29, 2018, on the same day the hospital received the lab result which was confirmed positive to the Lassa virus.</p>



<p>The State Government has however urged the residents in the state not to panic, “as the officials of the Ministry of Health are on top of the situation, conducting contact tracing on those who had contact with the victim.”</p>



<p>The State Government further stated that findings have shown that it is over 21 days since the victim was attended to at the hospital in Umuolu and Kwale and no case has since been discovered, however, contact tracing is still ongoing at FMC, Asaba.</p>



<p>As part of measures to curtail the spread of the virus, the State Government has urged residents of the state to cultivate good personal hygiene, clean and fumigate their environment regularly, encourage community hygiene to prevent rodents from entering homes and protect food from rats, and to report cases of strange fever to the nearest hospital.</p>



<p><strong><em>Channels</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-government-of-delta-state-has-confirmed-the-death-of-a-75-year-old-woman-as-a-result-of-lassa-fever/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Zimbabwe’s Health Ministry Declares Cholera Emergency As Death Toll Rises to 20</title>
		<link>/zimbabwes-health-ministry-declares-cholera-emergency-as-death-toll-rises-to-20/</link>
					<comments>/zimbabwes-health-ministry-declares-cholera-emergency-as-death-toll-rises-to-20/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 16:10:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10594</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to NAN, authorities on Monday announced that 18 people have died over the past week in the country’s capital. Following the death of 20 people and more than 2000 people infected after drinking contaminated water, the new Health Minister, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/zambiwa.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10595"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">According to NAN, authorities on Monday announced that 18 people have died over the past week in the country’s capital.</p>
</div></div>



<p>Following the death of 20 people and more than 2000 people infected after drinking contaminated water, the new Health Minister, Obadiah Moyo declared a Cholera Outbreak in Zimbabwe on Tuesday.</p>



<p><br>“We are declaring an emergency for Harare. This will allow us to contain typhoid, cholera, and whatever is going on.<br>“We don’t want any further deaths,” Moyo said after concluding a hospital tour in the capital.</p>



<p><br>According to NAN, authorities on Monday announced that 18 people have died over the past week in the country’s capital, Harare, and scores have been infected after cholera and typhoid outbreak in some areas.</p>



<p><br>These outbreaks are not alien as local authorities still battle with the challenges of providing clean water and appropriate sanitation facilities in the city, where slums without running water have slowly increased and whose infrastructure are failing due to decades of neglect.</p>



<p><br>A large number of suburbs go without running water for weeks, forcing residents to turn to unsafe sources.<br>NAN’s report also indicated that there was a cholera outbreak from August 2008 until June 2008.</p>



<p><br>The outbreak which began in Chitungwiza in Mashonaland East Province in August 2008, then spread to other parts of the country and by December 2008, cases were being reported in all 10 provinces.</p>



<p><br>The Zimbabwean government declared the outbreak a national crisis and called for international aid.<br>The epidemic peaked by January 2009 with nearly 8500 cases reported every week.</p>



<p><br>Cholera cases from this outbreak were also reported in neighbouring countries including South Africa, Malawi, Zambia, Mozambique, and Botswana.</p>



<p><br>The outbreak was brought under control with the help international agencies, and by July 2009 after no cases had been reported for several weeks, the Zimbabwean Ministry of Health officially declared the outbreak over.</p>



<p><br>A total of 98,596 cases of cholera and 4,369 deaths were reported, making it the largest case of cholera epidemic ever reported in Zimbabwean history.</p>



<p><br>The severity of the outbreak was blamed on poor sanitation, insufficient health infrastructure and limited access to health care services throughout Zimbabwe.</p>



<p>Reuters/NAN</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/zimbabwes-health-ministry-declares-cholera-emergency-as-death-toll-rises-to-20/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>1068 DIARRHOEA CASES RECORDED IN 10 BORNO LGAs</title>
		<link>/1068-diarrhoea-cases-recorded-in-10-borno-lgas/</link>
					<comments>/1068-diarrhoea-cases-recorded-in-10-borno-lgas/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 15:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10585</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Borno State has recorded 1068 cases of diarrhoea in 10 Local Government areas of the State. 1068 cases of diarrhoea have so far been recorded in Borno State. The State’s Commissioner for Health, Haruna Mshelia confirmed this while speaking to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/borno.png" alt="" class="wp-image-10586"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Borno State has recorded 1068 cases of diarrhoea in 10 Local Government areas of the State.</p>
</div></div>



<p>1068 cases of diarrhoea have so far been recorded in Borno State.</p>



<p>The State’s Commissioner for Health, Haruna Mshelia confirmed this while speaking to Channelstv reporters on Wednesday.</p>



<p>She stated that diarrhoea is a common occurrence in the State especially during the rainy season.</p>



<p>“Acute Diarrhoea is what we get all through the year from hospitals but not as an epidemic disease.”</p>



<p>“The cases were recorded between late May to August, with the highest recorded in August.”</p>



<p>Mshelia highlighted that Kukawa. Baga, Askira Uba, Bayo, Biu, Kwaya Kusar, were among the local governments affected by the disease.</p>



<p>She, however, said drugs have been distributed to affected persons while residents have been sensitized on basic diarrhoea preventive measures such as boiling water before drinking and other strict hygiene routines.</p>



<p><strong><em>Channelstv&nbsp; &nbsp;</em></strong></p>



<h3>Share Via</h3>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/1068-diarrhoea-cases-recorded-in-10-borno-lgas/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ebola Outbreak Spreads To A New DRC City Surrounded By High Insecurity</title>
		<link>/ebola-outbreak-spreads-to-a-new-drc-city-surrounded-by-high-insecurity/</link>
					<comments>/ebola-outbreak-spreads-to-a-new-drc-city-surrounded-by-high-insecurity/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 15:47:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10582</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Ebola outbreak in the Democratic Republic of Congo has spread to a city surrounded by insurgents, creating problems responders were “dreading,” the World Health Organisation said on Friday. One suspected case and one probable case have emerged in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Ebola-Outbreak.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10583"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">The Ebola outbreak in the Democratic Republic of Congo has spread to a city surrounded by insurgents, creating problems responders were “dreading,” the World Health Organisation said on Friday.</p>
</div></div>



<p>One suspected case and one probable case have emerged in the city of Oicha in DR Congo’s North Kivu Province, WHO’s emergency response chief; Peter Salama, told reporters on Friday.</p>



<p>While Oicha is not currently under rebel control, Salama said the city is mostly surrounded by territories held by a feared Ugandan insurgent group known as the Allied Democratic Forces (ADF).</p>



<p>“For the first time we have a confirmed case in an area with high insecurity,” Salama said.</p>



<p>“It really was the problem we were anticipating and the problem we were at the same time dreading.”</p>



<p>Countless civilians have been killed by unrest surrounding Oicha. Currently, priests, workers, and government employees are being held hostage there by insurgents, according to Salama.</p>



<p>The outbreak which began on August 1 in the North Kivu Town of Mangina is the 10<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;to hit DRC since 1976.</p>



<p>The hemorrhage fever has so far killed 63 people&#8211;out of the 103 confirmed or probable cases&#8211;but Salama warned that health workers were expecting “at least one additional wave of cases.”</p>



<p>The Oicha cases have now made containing the virus a very difficult task.</p>



<p>“We are going to have to operate in some very complex environments,” Salama said.</p>



<p>UN teams can only venture into Oicha with armed escorts.</p>



<p>If the number of patients or contacts of patients in the city increases, the logistical challenges and costs will also mount.</p>



<p>After it widely criticized the handling of the 2013-2016 West Africa Ebola Epidemic that killed 11,300 people, WHO has pledged to revamp its response systems.</p>



<p>The UN agency was widely praised for quickly containing an earlier outbreak in DR Congo’s northern Equateur province, but said from then on that restive North Kivu in the eastern part of the country posed additional challenges.</p>



<p>“We are quite at a pivotal moment in this outbreak. We are truly at crossroads.”</p>



<p><strong><em>AFP</em></strong></p>



<h3>Share Via</h3>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/ebola-outbreak-spreads-to-a-new-drc-city-surrounded-by-high-insecurity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DR Congo’s Ebola Deaths Rises To 49 With 2000 Feared ‘Contacts’</title>
		<link>/dr-congos-ebola-deaths-rises-to-49-with-2000-feared-contacts/</link>
					<comments>/dr-congos-ebola-deaths-rises-to-49-with-2000-feared-contacts/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 13:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10577</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Since the first reported case in the North Kivu Province on August 1, the current outbreak has killed 49 out of the 90 reported cases. The ongoing deadly Ebola Outbreak in the Eastern Part of the Democratic Republic of Congo [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Ebola-congo.png" alt="" class="wp-image-10578"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p>Since the first reported case in the North Kivu Province on August 1, the current outbreak has killed 49 out of the 90 reported cases.</p>
</div></div>



<p>The ongoing deadly Ebola Outbreak in the Eastern Part of the Democratic Republic of Congo has now claimed a total of 49 lives since the start of the month, the Government has said, and the World Health Organization expects even more cases in the coming weeks.</p>



<p>The increase in the number of Ebola-related deaths, coupled with a further 2000 people feared to have come in contact with the virus, adds to the growing number of woes of a country already battling with political uncertainty, violence, and displacement.</p>



<p>Since the first reported case in the North Kivu Province on August 1, the current outbreak has killed 49 out of the 90 reported cases, according to the latest bulletin released by the health ministry released on Saturday.</p>



<p>It highlighted that of the 49 deaths from the Ebola Virus, 27 cases were &#8216;probable&#8217; while 63 were confirmed. Confirmed cases are determined through laboratory tests carried out on blood samples taken from patients. Probable cases concerns sick people with a close epidemiological link to other confirmed cases, but who have not undergone testing.</p>



<p>Of the 49 deaths, 39 were recorded in Mangina, an agricultural village located 30 kilometres ( about 20 miles) Southwest of the city of Beni. Three deaths were also recorded in the neighbouring province of Ituri.</p>



<p>Field teams have identified 2,157 “contact”-people who may have come in contact with the deadly virus-according to the health ministry.</p>



<p>WHO spokesman Tarik Jasarevic while speaking to reporters on Friday from the UN agency’s Geneva headquarters said that it “expects more”.</p>



<p>“We don’t know if all the chains of transmission have been identified,” he said further.</p>



<p>The current outbreak is the 10th to hit the DRC since 1976 when Ebola was first identified and named after a river in the northern part of the country.</p>



<p>Ebola is still considered incurable, though quick isolation and rapid treatment of symptoms, such as diarrhea, vomiting, and dehydration have helped some patients to survive.</p>



<p>The need for a vaccine grew increasingly urgent when 11,300 died in an Ebola Epidemic that hit the West African States of Guinea, Sierra Leone, and Liberia in 2013-2015.</p>



<p><em><strong>AFP</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/dr-congos-ebola-deaths-rises-to-49-with-2000-feared-contacts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nine Confirmed Dead in DRC’s Recent Ebola Outbreak</title>
		<link>/nine-confirmed-dead-in-drcs-recent-ebola-outbreak/</link>
					<comments>/nine-confirmed-dead-in-drcs-recent-ebola-outbreak/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Medical Tutors]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 11:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[DISEASES]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10568</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nine confirmed Ebola victims have died since the virus resurfaced early this month in the Democratic Republic of Congo, the country’s Health Minister said on Tuesday. So far, nine confirmed Ebola victims have died since the virus resurfaced early this [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-media-text alignwide is-stacked-on-mobile"><figure class="wp-block-media-text__media"><img src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Ebola.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-10569"/></figure><div class="wp-block-media-text__content">
<p style="font-size:11px">Nine confirmed Ebola victims have died since the virus resurfaced early this month in the Democratic Republic of Congo, the country’s Health Minister said on Tuesday.</p>
</div></div>



<p>So far, nine confirmed Ebola victims have died since the virus resurfaced early this month in the Democratic Republic of Congo, the country’s Health Minister said on Tuesday.</p>



<p>Only seven deaths were previously announced, with the two latest victims also registered in the Beni region in North Kivu province.</p>



<p>&nbsp;On August 1, the health ministry announced the country’s 10th Ebola outbreak since 1976.</p>



<p>Thirty-three people had previously died in an outbreak in the northwest which was only declared over at the end of July.</p>



<p>“In total, 43 cases of hemorrhage fever have been reported in Beni region, with just 16 confirmed and 27 probable and 46 suspected cases are under investigation,” the ministry said on Tuesday.</p>



<p>Nearly 1000 people who have had “contact” with the virus have been registered in the health zones which are under surveillance, it said.</p>



<p>Ebola causes severe illness including vomiting, diarrhoea and some cases internal and external bleeding. If left untreated, Ebola can be fatal.</p>



<p>Authorities will begin targeted vaccination on Wednesday.</p>



<p>“Twelve teams of vaccinators will be deployed in different affected areas,” the ministry said while also confirming that teams have arrived in Beni.</p>



<p>The World Health Organization (WHO) has said that “the deterioration of the security situation” in areas affected was expected to be a major hindrance to response to the outbreak.</p>



<p>The Red Cross also announced that it was sending a “multidisciplinary” team of 19 people to Beni.</p>



<p><em><strong>AFP</strong></em></p>



<h3>Share Via</h3>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/nine-confirmed-dead-in-drcs-recent-ebola-outbreak/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
